Voices from the Food Revolution: People Who Changed The Way Americans Eat An oral history project conducted by Judith Weinraub Made possible with a grant from the Leon Levy Foundation 2009-2011 MSS 309
© 2010 Fales Library and Special Collections
Voices from the Food Revolution: People Who Changed The Way Americans Eat An oral history project conducted by Judith Weinraub
2009-2011
MSS 309
© 2010 Fales Library and Special Collections
43.0 interviews
Project Description
Voices from the Food Revolution: People Who Changed The Way Americans Eat
An oral history project conducted by Judith Weinraub
Ten years into the 21st century, food is a hot topic. Americans have learned that there are consequences to what we cook, eat, and feed our families. We acknowledge the relationship between our agricultural policy and the country's food system. We recognize cooking as a legitimate and increasingly popular career option and field of study. We lionize successful chefs.
Visitors from fifty years ago wouldn’t recognize today's preoccupation with food. They lived in a world where cherished new 'convenience' foods de-emphasized actual cooking, and the shelves at neighborhood grocery stores and supermarkets were lined with increasingly industrialized products. Fine restaurants of the time were mostly French. And nobody thought of taking on the American food system as a legitimate and desirable way to change the world.
But over time, post-WW II attitudes and buying habits as well as the arrival of new immigrant groups, the re-emergence of farmers markets, and a growing awareness of the consequences of eating poorly have slowly redefined our relationships with food.
The key landmarks are familiar, among them:
* Julia Child's books and television shows, which set new paradigms for learning how to cook
* the home cooks who were Child's devotees and demanded new ingredients, and more sophisticated equipment and the retailers who met that demand
* an increasing interest in foods from other cultures and a changing immigrant population that demanded and cooked with new ingredients
* the explosion of new cookbooks and food magazines
* the resurgence and growth of the farmers' market movement
* the huge expansion of the restaurant scene, which welcomed the latest food trends—nouvelle cuisine, comfort foods, regional foods and multi-cultural menus—and made celebrities of the chefs who cooked them
* food television
* an increasing awareness of problems in the American food supply
* the growing popularity of food issues as legitimate political concerns
* First Lady Michelle Obama's campaign to combat childhood obesity
* and, inevitably, the food writers and critics who chronicled these developments in newspapers, magazines, books and blogs
New York has had a defining role in this process.
This project is made up of oral history interviews conducted by Judith Weinraub with some of the people who have played key roles in these developments, among them writers, editors, food critics, farmers market initiators, entrepreneurs, distinguished chefs, and friends and colleagues of the late James Beard. The interviews are accompanied by introductory notes for each participant, as well as transcripts. In accordance with the accepted tenets of oral history interviewing, the participants have been allowed to delete and clarify material in the transcripts.
The interviewees:
In the beginning: James Beard and his circle: John Ferrone, Barbara Kafka, Irene Saks, Jane White Viazzi, Clark Wolf.
The activists: Barry Benepe, Hilary Baum, Dan Imhoff, Dan Barber
The carriers of change: Judith Jones, Gus Schumacher, Michael Batterberry and Ariane Batterberry
The writers and critics: Betty Fussell, Mimi Sheraton, Gael Greene
The entrepreneurs: Michael Whiteman, Reese Schonfeld, Tim Zagat and Nina Zagat
Two seminal educators and an early supporter of food studies: Jacques Pepin, Marion Nestle, Dalia Carmel
Television's Real Top Chefs: Lidia Bastianich, Tom Colicchio, and Madhur Jaffrey
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Acknowledgment
NYU Libraries thanks the Leon Levy Foundation for its generous support of Voices from the Food Revolution, an oral history project documenting the development of American foodways of the last half-century.
Bastianich, Lidia; Batterberry, Ariane Ruskin; Batterberry, Michael; Beard, James, 1903-1985; Benepe, Barry; Carmel, Dalia; Ferrone, John; Fussell, Betty Harper; Greene, Gael; Jaffrey, Madhur, 1933-; Jones, Judith, 1924-; Kafka, Barbara; Nestle, Marion; Pépin, Jacques; Sax, Irene; Schonfeld, Reese; Schumacher, Gus; Sheraton, Mimi; White, Jane; Whiteman, Michael; Wolf, Clark; Zagat, Nina; Zagat, Tim; Cookery, American |x History |y 20th century.; Food industry and trade; Food Writers; interviews; oral histories (document genres); Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.; Transcripts.
- Dan Barber
  Biographical Note
  The youngest person to be interviewed for this project (a 1992 graduate of Tufts University), Dan Barber is nevertheless a celebrity chef with multiple James Beard Foundation awards to his credit. He is well-known, not only for his restaurants: Blue Hill in New York's Greenwich Village and Blue Hill at Stones Barns in Westchester County on the Rockefeller family estate in Pocantico Hills about an hour's drive from Manhattan, but also for his role as an advocate for a sustainable approach to cooking and a healthier food system.
  A popular speaker and frequent writer on these issues, in 2009 Barber was included in Time Magazine's annual list of the world's most influential people. Barber is a member of President Barack Obama's Council on Physical Fitness, Sports and Nutrition as well as the Advisory Board to the Harvard Medical School Center for Health and The Global Environment.
  This interview covers his early life, education and development as a chef—he insists he wasn't all that good a cook when he started out—and as an advocate for healthy, responsible, flavorful eating.
  Access Points
  People:
  Barber, Dan
  Barber. David
  Barber. Laureen
  Batterberry, Michael
  Bouley, David
  Rockefeller, David, 1915-
  Shipley, David, 1963-
  Organizations:
  Blue Hill Farm (Great Barrington, Mass)
  Blue Hill (Restaurant)
  La Cigale (Restaurant)
  President’s Council on Fitness, Sports & Nutrition (U.S.)
  Stone Barns Center for Food and Agriculture (Pocantico Hills, N.Y)
  Subjects:
  Agricultural processing industries
  Community-supported agriculture
  Cooking, American
  Dinners and dining
  Farm produce
  Farmer’s markets
  Farrming
  Food industry and trade -- United States
  Gastronomy
  Local foods
  Restaurant management
  Barber, Dan; Barber, David; Barber, Laureen; Batterberry, Michael; Blue Hill (Restaurant).; Blue Hill Farm (Great Barrington, Mass).; Bouley, David; La Cigale (Restaurant).; President's Council on Fitness, Sports, and Nutrition (U.S.).; Rockefeller, David, 1915-; Shipley, David, 1963-; Stone Barns Center for Food and Agriculture (Pocantico Hills, N.Y.).; Agricultural processing industries; Community -supported agriculture; Cooking, American; Dinners and dining; Farm produce; Farmer's markets; Farming; Food industry and trade |z United States.; Gastronomy.; Local foods; Restaurant management
  - Interview 1, February 15, 2011
  - Interview 2, March 8, 2011
  - Interview 3, March 15, 2011
- Lidia Bastianich
  The acclaimed cookbook author, television personality, restaurateur, chef and businesswoman Lidia Bastianich was a little girl when the Catholic Charities rescued her family from a Displaced Persons camp in Italy and brought them to the United States after their native Istria was was absorbed by Yugoslavia and communism.
  Growing up in Queens, Bastianich originally hoped to become a pediatrician. But years helping to cook for her family, a part-time job in a local bakery while she was still in school and marriage to an Italian man working in the restaurant business reoriented her life.
  Today she is one of the best-known chefs in the United States, thanks to her ongoing popular cooking programs on PBS and her many cookbooks. With her son Joseph Bastianich and chef Mario Batali, she is also a partner in a mini-empire of Italian restaurants in New York, Kansas City and Pittsburgh.
  This interview tracks over her early life in Italy and America, her young adulthood, her marriage and first restaurants in Queens with her husband, their entry into the New York restaurant world with the acclaimed Felidia, the challenges of being a mother at the same time she ran the restaurant and the growth of her business since then. Throughout it all, Bastianich has made her family an important part of her business and of her television series.
  Bastianich, Joesph
  Bastianich, Lidia
  Batali, Mario
  Manuali, Tanya Bastianich
  Nicotra, Fortunato
  Felidia (Restaurant)
  Authorship
  Cooking, Italian
  Friuli Venezia Giulia (Italy)
  Immigration
  Restaurants
  Television cooking shows
  Yugoslavia -- Emigration and immigration
  Bastianich, Joseph; Bastianich, Lidia; Batali, Mario; Felidia (Restaurant).; Manuali, Tanya Bastianich; Nicotra, Fortunato; Authorship; Cooking, Italian; Dinners and dining; Friuli Venezia Giulia |z Italy; Gastronomy.; Immigration; Restaurant management; Restaurants; Television cooking shows; Yugoslavia |x Emigration and immigration
  - Interview 1, March 24, 2011
  - Interview 2, April 4, 2011
- Ariane Batterberry
  Michael and Ariane Batterberry worked together in publishing from the late 1960s until 2010. Michael Batterberry died of cancer on July 28, 2010 in Manhattan at the age of 78.
  Initially, the couple wrote on the history of art and culture. The switch to food began with On The Town in New York, A History of Restaurants from 1776-1976, and generated two ground-breaking magazines: Food and Wine and Food Arts. Together, they helped change the way people think about food.
  In the early 1960s, the Batterberrys met and became friends with James Beard and subsequently became frequent dinner guests at each other's homes. Beard particularly liked Michael Batterberry's cooking--so much so that Beard invited him to teach a class as part of his Great Cooks series.
  In recent years, Michael Batterberry took an active role in educating Americans about problems with the American food system. He was an articulate advocate for small farmers, especially immigrant farmers, and a founding director of Wholesome Wave Foundation, which works to bring fresh, locally grown, affordable food to underserved communities.
  The Batterberrys each discuss their early lives (he on several continents and she on the Upper East Side of Manhattan and in London) and their professional lives.
  Batterberry, Ariane Ruskin
  Beard, James, 1903-1985
  Johnson, Hugh, 1939-
  Food Arts
  Food & wine (New York, N.Y.)
  Pantheon Books
  Cooking, American -- History -- 20th century
  Feminism
  Food habits -- New York (State) -- New York
  Menus
  Publishers and publishing
  Restaurants -- New York (State) -- New York
  Sex role – Unites States -- History -- 20th century
  Sexual division of labor -- United States
  Batterberry, Ariane Ruskin; Batterberry, Michael; Beard, James, 1903-1985; Food & wine (New York, N.Y.).; Food Arts.; Johnson, Hugh, 1939-; Pantheon Books.; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th Century; Dinners and dining; Feminism.; Food habits |z New York (State) |z New York; Gastronomy.; Menus.; Publishers and publishing; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.; Sex role |z United States |x History |y 20th century; Sexual division of labor |z United States
  - Interview 1, May 27, 2009
    Scope and Content
    Running time: 1 hour, 7 minutes
- Michael Batterberry
  Bricktop, 1894-1984
  Claiborne, Craig
  Dinesen, Isak, 1885-1962
  Grandi, Tony
  Prudhomme, Paul
  Schumacher, Gus
  Stewart, Martha
  Waters, Alice
  American Express Company
  Batterberry Associates
  Bloomingdale's (Firm)
  Good living (Television program)
  Gourmet
  Playboy Enterprises
  Wholesome Wave Foundation
  Cooking -- Periodicals
  Electronic publishing
  Food writing
  Restaurants -- Italy -- Rome
  Restaurants -- Venezuela -- Caracas
  American Express Company.; Batterberry Associates.; Batterberry, Ariane Ruskin; Batterberry, Michael; Beard, James, 1903-1985; Bloomingdale's (Firm).; Bricktop, 1894-1984; Claiborne, Craig; Dinesen, Isak, 1885-1962; Food & wine (New York, N.Y.).; Food Arts.; Good living (Television program).; Gourmet.; Grandi, Tony; Playboy Enterprises.; Prudhomme, Paul; Schumacher, Gus; Stewart, Martha; Waters, Alice; Wholesome Wave Foundation.; Cooking |v Periodicals; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th Century; Dinners and dining; Electronic publishing; Food industry and trade |z United States.; Food writing.; Gastronomy.; Local foods; Publishers and publishing; Restaurants |z Italy |z Rome; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.; Restaurants |z Venezuela |Z Caracas; Television cooking shows
  - Interview 1, May 8, 2009
    Running time: 1 hour, 20 minutes
  - Interview 2, May 27, 2009
    Running time: 1 hour, 42 minutes
- Hilary Baum
  Hilary Baum is a pioneer in the movement to bring attention to problems and possibilities of the American food system, and New York in particular. She is the Director of the Baum Forum, a program that includes conferences and seminars focusing on food and agricultural issues, and the President of Public Market Partners.
  Baum is also the co-founder, with Fern Gail Estrow, of Food Systems Network NYC, a collaborative that brings together representatives from food-related non-profits, government agencies, and private citizens interested in the worlds of: food safety and food justice; farmers' markets; public markets; agricultural marketing programs; and community supported agriculture.
  Her childhood and early life, however, took place in a more rarified corner of the New York food world. Her father, the prescient Joe Baum, was the force behind The Four Seasons, Windows on the World, and The Rainbow Room—places that redefined what restaurants and the restaurant experience could be. Through her parents, she met legendary figures in that world like James Beard, a family friend.
  This interview tracks her childhood, in particular the ways in which her grandparents and parents' businesses, as well has their food world friends, influenced her choice of career. She also talks about her work in the food production business (with her mother), her recollections of James Beard, her early support for farmers and farmers markets, and her work with the Baum Forum today.
  Aaron, Florence
  Baum, Ruth
  Baum, Joseph
  Hamilton, Dorothy M.
  Lewis, Bob
  Culinary Institute of America
  Food Systems Network
  Four Seasons (Restaurant)
  Greenmarket
  New York City Food and Fitness Partnership
  Project for Public Spaces
  Public Market Collaborative
  Restaurant Associates
  Windows on the World (New York, N.Y.)
  World Trade Center (New York, N.Y.)
  Community -supported agriculture
  Farm produce -- Marketing
  Food industry and trade -- New York (State) -- New York
  Food service
  Produce trade
  School children -- Food
  Women in the food industry
  Aaron, Florence; Baum, Joseph; Baum, Ruth; Beard, James, 1903-1985; Culinary Institute of America.; Food Systems Network.; Four Seasons (Restaurant).; Greenmarket.; Hamilton, Dorothy M.; Lewis, Bob; New York City Food and Fitness Partnership.; Project for Public Spaces.; Public Market Collaborative.; Restaurant Associates.; Windows on the World (New York, N.Y.).; World Trade Center (New York, N.Y.).; Agricultural processing industries; Community -supported agriculture; Farm produce |x Marketing; Farmer's markets; Food industry and trade |z New York (State) |z New York; Food service; Local foods; Produce trade; Restaurant management; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.; School children |x Food; Women in the food industry
  - Interview 1, September 22, 2009
    Running time: 1 hour, 29 minutes
- Barry Benepe
  In 1976, the post-World War II habits of supermarket shopping still ruled American kitchens. Fresh fruits and vegetables were limited to summertime roadside stands. To most urban dwellers, farmers were distant exotic creatures. It would be decades before words like local, seasonal, and organic became commonplace.
  Brought to life by Architect Barry Benepe and urban planner Robert Lewis, the Greemarket movement was a major development that helped to change that way of thinking. This movement initiated consumer appreciation—and eventually demand for—fresh food.
  At the time, Benepe was the director of his own small firm and therefore not bound by traditional notions of architectural practice, allowing him to expand into unorthodox areas such as open space protection and farmland preservation. Lewis applied for a job at his firm. Together they saw the disconnect between the food to which New Yorkers had access in standard supermarkets, and the much fresher, higher quality food produced by area farmers—and the possibility of bringing the two together. When they located an unused and vacant city lot behind Bloomingdales on Manhattan's Upper East Side, they jumpstarted the New York City Greenmarket movement.
  In these interviews, Benepe talks about his childhood in New York and on a family farm in Maryland, his education, his early architectural practice, the start-up of the Greenmarkets and what followed. Today, the original market is one of 50 in all five boroughs and has served as a model for markets all over the country.
  Benepe, Adrian
  Benepe, Barry
  Conklin, William J.
  Jacobs, Jane, 1916-2006
  McPhee, John, 1931-
  Rossant, James S., 1928-2009
  Weinberg, Robert C. (Robert Charles), 1901-1974
  Council on the Environment of New York City
  New York (N.Y.). Dept. of Parks and Recreation
  New York (N.Y.). Dept. of City Planning
  Union Square Community Coalition
  Architecture
  City planning
  Community supported agriculture
  Farmers -- New Jersey
  Farmers -- New York (State)
  Food industry and trade
  High Line (New York, N.Y.)
  Historic preservation
  Newcastle upon Tyne (England)
  Newburgh (N.Y.)
  Saugerties (N.Y.)
  Union Square (New York, N.Y.)
  Washington Square (New York, N.Y.)
  Benepe, Adrian; Benepe, Barry; Conklin, William J.; Council on the Environment of New York City.; Greenmarket.; Jacobs, Jane, 1916-2006; Lewis, Bob; McPhee, John, 1931-; New York (N.Y.). Dept. of City Planning.; New York (N.Y.). Dept. of Parks and Recreation.; Rossant, James S., 1928-2009; Union Square Community Coalition.; Weinberg, Robert C., (Robert Charles), 1901-1974; Architecture; City planning; Community -supported agriculture; Farm produce |x Marketing; Farmer's markets; Farmers |z New Jersey; Farmers |z New York (State); Food industry and trade; High Line (New York, N.Y.); Historic preservation; Local foods; Newburgh (N.Y.); Newcastle upon Tyne (England); Produce trade; Saugerties (N.Y.); Union Square (New York, N.Y.); Washington Square (New York, N.Y.)
  - Interview 1, June 25, 2010
    Running time: 2 hours, 7 minutes
  - Interview 2, July 13, 2010
- Dalia Carmel
  Food scholar Dalia Carmel has been called "the angel of American food writers" because she made her 11,000-volume personal library of cookbooks available to all who asked. Assembled over 40 years, the library covers nearly every geographical area, ethnicity, and ingredient.
  Born in Israel, Carmel came to the United States in 1960. She had been inadvertently caught up in Operation Suzannah, a 1954 plot to undermine international support for Egypt as a reliable administrator of the Suez Canal. When the operation failed, it morphed into a political quagmire known as the Lavon Affair. Because Carmel, then a young soldier working in the Finance Ministry, had, under orders, altered a document related to the affair, she unhappily became a public figure.
  Carmel discusses the Lavon Affair; her eventual decision to leave Israel, first for London and eventually—she thought temporarily—for the United States; the gradual development of her cookbook collection, and her decision to donate the volumes to the Fales Library.
  Avigur, Shaoul
  Ben-Gurion, David, 1886-1973
  Brown, Bianca
  Carmel, Dalia
  De Silva, Cara
  Eshkol, Levi, 1895-1969
  Gibli, Binyamin
  Goldstein, Herbert
  Hausner, Gideon, 1915-1990
  Kirshenblatt-Gimblett, Barbara
  Lavon, Pinchas
  Nestle, Marion
  Pachter, Mina
  Peer, Edith
  Stern, Annie
  Taube, Judith
  Taylor, Marvin J.
  El al, netive aṿir le-Yiśrael (El Al Israel Airlines)
  Fales Library
  Yad ṿa-shem, rashut ha-zikaron la-Shoah ṿela-gevurah (Yad Vashem, Jerusalem)
  Book collecting
  Cookbooks
  Cooking, Jewish -- History -- 20th century
  Concentration camp inmates’ writings
  Entertaining
  International cooking
  Israel -- Politics and government -- 1948-1967
  Avigur, Shaoul; Ben-Gurion, David, 1886-1973; Brown, Bianca; Carmel, Dalia; De Silva, Cara; El al, netive ayir le-Yiśrael (El Al Israel Airlines).; Eshkol, Levi, 1895-1969; Fales Library.; Gibli, Binyamin; Goldstein, Herbert; Hausner, Gideon, 1915-1990; Kieshenblatt-Gimblett, Barbara; Lavon, Pinchas; Nestle, Marion; Pachter, Mina; Peer, Edith; Stern, Annie; Taub, Judith; Taylor, Marvin J.; Yad va-shem, rashut ha-zikaron la0Shoah vela-gevurah (Yad Vashem, Jerusalem).; Book collecting.; Concentration camp inmate's writings; Cookbooks.; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th Century; Cooking, Jewish |x History |y 20th century; Dinners and dining; Entertaining; Gastronomy.; International cooking; Israel |x Politics and government |y 1948-1967; Publishers and publishing
  - Interview 1, September 24, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour, 37 minutes
  - Interview 2, October 1, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour, 13 minutes
- Tom Colicchio
  One of the byproducts of the food revolution is the increasing respect for chefs. Along with that and the attention to the profession given by the media, a new category has emerged—the Celebrity Chef. No one of them is better-known than Tom Colicchio. Already a highly respected and well-reviewed chef and restaurateur when he became the head judge of the wildly popular television program Top Chef, Colicchio is probably the best-known chef in America.
  As a young teenager, he started cooking at home, discovered he enjoyed it and worked his way through a swim club food concession, a Burger King, and increasingly more ambitious restaurants in his native New Jersey before heading to Manhattan. His teachers were his on-the-jobs training, the chefs he worked for there and in New York and books, especially Jacques Pepin's on method and technique.
  He came to wide attention at the Gramercy Tavern in New York's Flatiron district, and then at Craft nearby.
  The recipient of five James Beard Foundation awards, today Colichio and his cooking can be seen not only at the Craft restaurants (including Craftbar and Craftsteak) in New York, LA, Dallas, and Las Vegas), but also at Colicchio and Sons in Manhattan's Meatpacking District. In 2003, Colicchio and two partners founded the more affordable sandwich and salad outlets, 'wichcraft. In 2010 his work at Craft was honored when the Beard Foundation named him the country's Outstanding Chef.
  Colicchio is married to his frequent writing partner, the documentary filmmaker Lori Silverbush.
  Bras, Michel
  Bryan, Jerry
  Colicchio, Tom
  Keller, Thomas, 1955-
  Meyer, Danny
  Portale, Alfred
  Silverbush, Lori
  Wine, Barry
  Colicchio & Sons (Restaurant)
  Craft (Restaurant)
  Food Research and Action Center
  Gramercy Tavern
  Mondrian (Restaurant)
  Top chef (Television Program)
  Cooking
  Nutrition